What happens to the health of
our colon within just two weeks
after switching from a standard American
diet to one centered around plants?
Watch the video to find out.
"The Best Dietary Changes
for Colon Cancer Prevention"
We have 100 trillion micro-organisms
residing in our gut,
give or take a few trillion, but
“the spread of the Western lifestyle
has been accompanied
by microbial changes,”
which may be contributing to our
epidemics of chronic disease.
The problem is that we’re
eating these meat-sweet diets,
characterized by a high intake
of animal products, sugars,
processed foods, and a low
intake of whole plant foods.
Contrary to the fermentation of
the carbohydrates that make it down
to our colon—the fiber and
resistant starch that benefit us
through the generation of these
magical short chain fatty acids
like butyrate—microbial
protein fermentation,
when excess protein is consumed…
that generates potentially toxic
and pro-carcinogenic metabolites
involved in colorectal cancer.
And so, what we eat
can cause an imbalance
in our gut microbiome and
potentially create a ‘recipe’
for colorectal cancer,
where a high-fat, high-meat,
high processed food diet tips the scale
towards dysbiosis and
colorectal cancer,
whereas a high-fiber and starch,
lower meat diet can pull you back
into symbiosis with your friendly
flora and away from cancer.
We now have evidence from
interventional studies
suggesting that “adopting a plant-based,
minimally processed high-fiber diet
may rapidly reverse the effects of
meat-based diets on
the gut microbiome.”
So, what may be a new form of
personalized microbiome
medicine for chronic disease?
It’s called food, which can
rapidly and reproducibly
alter the human gut microbiome.
Switch people between a whole
food plant-based diet
and more of an animal
food-based diet,
and you can see dramatic
shifts within two days,
which can result in
toxic metabolites.
Switch people to an
animal food-based diet
and levels of deoxycholic
acid go up,
which is a secondary bile
acid known to promote
DNA damage and liver cancers.
Why do levels go up?
Because the bad bacteria
producing the stuff
triple—in just two days.
And over time the richness
of the microbial diversity
in our gut is disappearing.
Here’s our bacterial tree of
life that’s getting depleted.
Why is this happening?
The fiber gap.
“A low-fiber diet is a key
driver of microbiome depletion.”
Yeah, there’s antibiotics,
and cesarean sections,
and indoor plumbing,
but the only factor
that has been empirically
demonstrated to be important
is a diet low in MACs
(not Big Macs),
microbiota-accessible carbohydrates,
which is just a fancy name
for fiber found in a whole
plant foods and resistant starch
found mostly in beans, peas,
lentils, and whole grains.
Our intake of dietary fiber,
our intake of whole plant foods,
is negligibly low
in the Western world
when compared to what we evolved
to eat over millions of years.
Such a low-fiber diet provides
insufficient nutrients for
our gut microbes, leading
not only to the loss
of bacterial diversity and richness,
but also to the reduction
in the production
of those beneficial
fermentation end products
that they make with the fiber.
We are in effect, starving
our microbial self.
What are we going to do about
the deleterious consequences
of a diet deficient
in whole plant foods?
Create new-fangled functional foods,
of course, and supplements,
and drugs—prebiotics,
probiotics, synbiotics.
Think how much money
there is to be made!
Or, we could just eat the way
our bodies were meant to eat.
What kind of value is that going
to get your stockholders, though?
Don’t you know probiotic
pills may be the next
big source of big
pharma billions?
Why eat healthy though, when
you can just have someone else
eat healthy for you and
then get a fecal transplant
from a vegan!
Researchers compared the microbiomes
of vegans versus omnivores,
and found the vegan’s friendly
flora were churning out
more of the good stuff,
showing that a plant-based diet
may result in more beneficial
metabolites in the bloodstream
and less of the bad
stuff like TMAO.
But while the impact
of a vegan diet
on what the bacteria
were making was large,
the effect on the composition
of the gut microbiome
was surprisingly modest.
They only found “slight differences
between the gut microbiomes
of omnivores versus vegans”?
That was a shocker to the researchers;
this very modest difference
juxtaposed against
the significantly enhanced
dietary consumption
of fermentable plant foods.
The vegans were eating
nearly twice the fiber.
Anyone see the problem here?
The vegans just barely made the
minimum daily intake of fiber.
Why?
Because Oreos are vegan,
Cocoa Pebbles are vegan,
french fries, Coke, potato chips,
there are vegan Doritos and Pop-Tarts.
You can eat a terrible vegan diet.
Burkitt showed that you need
to get at least 50 grams a day
(of fiber) for colon
cancer prevention.
That’s only half of what our
bodies were designed to get.
We evolved getting
about 100 grams a day.
And that’s what you see
in modern populations
that are immune to
epidemic colorectal cancer.
So, what if instead of
feeding people a vegan diet,
you just fed people
that kind of diet,
a diet centered around
whole plant foods?
We’ll find out next.
Colon cancer is our second
leading cancer killer,
but some places,like rural Africa,
have more than 10 times
lower rates than we do.
The reason we know it’s
not genetic is that
“migrant studies, such as
those in Japanese Hawaiians,
have demonstrated that it
only takes one generation
for the immigrant population
to assume the colon
cancer incidence
of the host Western population.”
Now, the change in
diet is considered
most probably responsible for this.
But there are all
sorts of changes
when you move from
one culture to another—
like smoking rates, different
exposures to chemicals,
infections, antibiotics.
You don’t know if it’s the diet…
until you put it to the test.
It's rare I do a whole
video on a single study,
but I think you’ll agree
this one is worth it.
This international group of researchers
were trying to find out
why colon cancer rates
were an order of
magnitude higher here—
in African Americans and Caucasians—
than in rural Africa.
Well, if you look at American
colons, they’re a mess:
polyps, diverticulosis—
not to mention hemorrhoids—
whereas the African colons
were remarkably pristine.
And more importantly,
sevenfold lower
colonic epithelial
proliferation rates,
a characteristic of
precancerous conditions.
They measured everything
that they were eating
and concluded that the higher
colorectal cancer risk
and proliferation rates
were most closely
“associated with higher dietary
intakes of animal products”,
which may have led to
“higher colonic populations
of these potentially toxic [acid]
and bile-salt-producing bacteria.”
But you don’t know…
until you put it to the test.
Higher rates are
associated with higher
animal protein and animal fat,
lower fiber consumption,
more of those bad bile acids,
less of those good short chain
fatty acids like butyrate,
and that higher
mucosal proliferation.
But how do we know it’s the
diet that’s mucking things up?
You don’t know…
until you perform an
interventional study.
How about we just
swap their diets?
Feed the Americans a high-
fiber African-style diet,
and those poor Africans get the SAD,
Standard American Diet,
like sausage and white flour
pancakes for breakfast,
a burger and fries for lunch,
and like some meatloaf
and white rice for supper.
That was day one for the rural
Africans in the experiment,
whereas the Americans
were forced to eat
fruits and vegetables,
corn and beans.
To help with compliance they
threw in more familiar foods
like veggie dogs, though
note it was not a vegan diet,
just generally plant-based.
And the food exchanges
weren’t for years,
but just two weeks.
Could they see changes that fast?
The dietary changes
resulted in remarkable
reciprocal changes in the
lining of their colons
in terms of cancer risk
and their microbiome.
Switching to plant-based boosted
the fiber fermentation
and suppressed the carcinogenic
bile acid synthesis.
Let’s look at some before
and after pictures.
They took biopsies, and
this is the colon lining
of an African American
under a microscope.
Those brown dots
mark dividing cells;
their colon lining was in overdrive,
the cells rapidly dividing,
a sign of premalignancy,
a risk factor for cancer.
But just two weeks
eating a healthier diet,
and their colons calmed right down.
The African Africans started
out with some proliferation,
but it got worse on
the American diet.
This is a different marker
measuring inflammation.
Each of the brown dots here
represents an inflammatory cell;
so, rife inflammation before
calmed way down after
just two weeks,
and the opposite in
those eating worse.
We know that when our friendly
flora ferment fiber,
they produce beneficial
compounds like butyrate,
which is anti-inflammatory
and anti-cancer.
Well, impressively,
‘Africanization’ of the diet
more than doubled butyrate production,
whereas ‘Westernization’ cut it in half.
In terms of toxic metabolites,
a significant drop on the healthier diet,
whereas the ‘meatloafy’
diet increased the levels
of these carcinogens by 400%
within just two weeks.
So, bottom line (no pun intended):
what they were able to show is
that just by changing the food,
you can remarkably
change your risk.
In fact, that’s how the
lead investigator put it:
“change your diet,
change your cancer risk!”
It may be never too late
to start eating healthier.
Based on these kind of data,
“adopting a whole-food vegan
or [even just] near-vegan diet
rich in fruits and vegetables,”
along with other healthy
lifestyle decisions,
“could have a stunningly
positive impact
on the cancer risks not
only of black Americans,
but of all peoples.”
“While it [might] be
unrealistic to expect
rapid and profound lifestyle changes
in the general population,
[hey]…at least we have
sound, effective advice to offer
to those who [make the choice]
to take the steps needed to
optimize their healthful longevity.”